Welcome back to Apush in under 3
minutes. No time for intros, let's get
into it. It's time to talk about World
War II. This war will be like no other
in history. The US will directly fight
Japan in the Pacific theater, and the
Allied powers will fight Germany in
Europe. After Pearl Harbor and
Congress's declaration of war, Americans
will view this war as a fight for the
survival of freedom and democracy
against fascist and militaristic
ideologies. And this view on the war
isn't too far off from the truth because
later in the war, it was realized the
horrible things the Axis powers were up
to. In Germany, minorities with a
special emphasis on Jewish citizens will
be forced into horrible concentration
death camps where it is said that over 6
million Jewish will die. Over in Japan,
their invasion of China will showcase
horrific tragedies such as the rape of
Nanking where Chinese civilians and
disarmed soldiers were mass murdered,
raped, and looted. Fascism posed such a
threat that this war was about more than
just victory or defeat like in World War
I. The Allies had to win or the world
would be fundamentally changed. America
quickly recognized this leading to full
national mobilization. Industry surged
and women and minorities joined the war
effort through groups like the Women's
Army Auxiliary Corps and AJA units of
Japanese-American soldiers. So, let's go
over to the war now. We'll first talk
about the European theater. Basically,
by 1944, Germany had conquered France
and part of the Soviet Union. On the
eastern side, the winter allowed the
Soviets to regroup and push back against
Germany with probably the most important
turning point battle in world history
being the Battle of Stalingrad. On the
western side, the Allies needed to push
back against Germany. So, on June 6th,
1944, a combination of American,
British, and Canadian forces stormed the
northern beaches of France which was
known as D-Day. This was a huge success
and the Allied forces will continue
pushing on the west while the Soviets
will push on the east and eventually
Hitler will be defeated. Now, let's head
over to the Pacific theater. The turning
point battle here is when America will
destroy a bunch of Japanese aircraft
carriers and that will happen at the
Battle of Midway. After Midway, America
will start taking back islands that
Japan had conquered during the war.
However, this will reveal a grim
reality. Japanese soldiers fought with
extreme brutality, and their code of
honor compelled them to fight to the
death, making the island-hopping
campaign extremely brutal and costly. By
the end of the war, America had
developed the atomic bomb thanks to the
Manhattan Project. This bomb would kill
so many people, but it could force the
fierce Japanese to surrender. And with
so many American soldiers dying in this
island-hopping, America would be forced
to make a difficult choice. And I think
Oppenheimer will put it best.
>> Now I am become death,
the destroyer of worlds.
>> Two A-bombs will be dropped. Hundreds of
thousands of innocent people will die.
Japan will surrender, and it will be one
of the biggest moral debates for the
rest of history. On the screen now are
AP-style questions for this topic. Pause
now.
I'll put the answers on the screen now.
I will see you in the next one.